<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the Cathedral Church of Worcester on the 29th of May, 1684 being the anniversary day of His Majesty's birth, and happy restauration / by George Hickes ...</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20005</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12222135</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12222135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56434</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43673)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56434)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 919:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the Cathedral Church of Worcester on the 29th of May, 1684 being the anniversary day of His Majesty's birth, and happy restauration / by George Hickes ...</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.E. for Walter Kettilby ... and John Jones ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XIV, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56434:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56434:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the <hi>Cathedral Church</hi> OF WORCESTER, On the 29th of <hi>May,</hi> 1684. Being the ANNIVERSARY DAY OF HIS MAJESTY'S Birth, and Happy Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Hickes,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in Ordinary to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Joint and Earneſt Requeſt of the</hi> MAYOR, <hi>and</hi> ALDERMEN <hi>of</hi> Worceſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. E.</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>John Jones</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Worceſter,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56434:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56434:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>FRANCIS HAINES</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> MAYOR, And to the Worſhipful the ALDERMEN Of the City of Worceſter.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE ſtyle of the Paper, in which you ſent me your joint and earneſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to publiſh this Diſcourſe, was ſo reſpectful and obliging, that I could not deny it without incurring the imputation of
<pb facs="tcp:56434:3"/>Rudeneſs, eſpecially ſeing it was the firſt Requeſt, of any Kind, that you ever deſired of me.</p>
                  <p>I need not tell the world, how Loyal you are, nor how Active ſome of you have been in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming this City, the very Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of this Sermon, which all the Enemies of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be ſure to Condemn, is a ſufficient Teſtification, that you are ſome of thoſe Worthy Citizens, who in the late diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Times were too honeſt, and too wiſe to be miſled by thoſe ſubtle and malicious Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Monarchy, who are generally known by this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, that they are for the King againſt his Evil Counſellors, and for the Proteſtant Religion againſt the Church.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:56434:3"/>
                  <p>I was very much pleaſed, as well as ſurprized, to find at my arrival on the Evening of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſary Day of our moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraigns Birth, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Return, that this City, now reſtored to its ſelf, had prepared to celebrate that Auſpicious day in a moſt Solemn, and Feſtival manner; and I muſt bear you and your Loyal Citizens witneſs, that I never ſaw more Conduct and Order in any Publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, more Gravity in any Publick Joy, or more univerſal Temperance, and Sobriety at any Publick Feaſting among all Sorts of Perſons, exactly agreeable to that ſeaſonable Exhortation, with which I concluded this Sermon, which now is no longer mine, but <hi>Yours.</hi> I am very ſenſible it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb facs="tcp:56434:4"/>not half of that great Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which you have expreſſed of it, and if it anſwer thoſe Ends, but in any tolerable and compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meaſure, for which you deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me to make it publick, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially among the People of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to whom I am bound to have a particular regard, I ſhall think my pains well ſpent, and rejoyce that I was ſo happy, as to teſtify in a way ſo ſerviceable to the Publick that I am.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Gentlemen, <hi>Your moſt Affectionate, and Faithful Friend, and humble Servant,</hi> George Hickes. Pſalm.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56434:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. XIV. v. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When the Lord bringeth back the Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his People, <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be glad.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The whole Verſe runs thus:</hi> O that the Salvation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were come out of <hi>Sion!</hi> when the Lord bringeth back, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS and the foregoing Pſalm, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>David</hi> in the Rebellion of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi> when the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally revolted from the Allegiance which they owed to him, and the Duty which they owed to God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Verſe he gives us an account of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and Ring leaders of this general Apoſtacy, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: They were, it ſeems, an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> of Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and Atheiſtical Men, who tho' they durſt not openly deny the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with their Mouths, yet they denied his Being, and Providence, or at leaſt doubted of them in their hearts, <hi>The Fool hath ſaid in his Heart, there is no God;</hi> meaning moſt likely the Fool <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or perhaps the Raw, and Younger Fool <hi>Abſolom.</hi> And then for thoſe that were of their Party, <hi>they are,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>corrupt, they have done abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56434:5"/>works, there is none that doth good.</hi> And then in the third Verſe, to ſhew how the Generality of the Nation had in a manner loſt all Senſe of their Duty, <hi>they are all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>gone aſide, they are all together become filthy,</hi> or putrid, <hi>there is none that doth good, no not one.</hi> In the fourth Verſe, He expreſſes his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment at the ſtupidity, and blindneſs of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators,</hi> that they ſhould go on without any Senſe, or remorſe, in their Atheiſtical Practices of Rebellion, and be ſo unjuſt, and irreligious: <hi>Have all the workers of Iniquity no Knowledge, who eat up my People, as they eat Bread, and call not upon the Lord.</hi> In the fifth Verſe, he tells us, that the Generality of the People, were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with fear to joyn with them, but that it was a cauſeleſs miſtruſt, and fear, for want of conſidering, That God will protect Righteous men, and Cauſes. <hi>There were they in great fear,<note place="margin">He addeth, in a Parallel place, <hi>Pſal. 53.5.</hi> where no fear was.</note> for God is in the Generation of the Righteous.</hi> i. e. they were in a great fear, fearing men more than God, who taketh part with the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous aginſt the Wicked. In the ſixth Verſe, he ſhews how the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> laughed at the ſmall Loyal Party, which preferring their Duty, before their Intereſt, and truſting in the Protection of Heaven, adhered to the King, <hi>You have ſhamed the Counſel of the Poor, becauſe the Lord is his Refuge.</hi> i. e. you have mocked and jeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Poor Deſpicable <hi>Loyal Party, becauſe they make the Lord their Refuge.</hi> And then in the laſt Verſe, he expreſſeth a great, and longing deſire for that happy time, when God, who dwelt in <hi>Sion,</hi> would ariſe, and ſhew himſelf in the Deliverance of him, and his People, <hi>O that the Salvation,</hi> (or Saviour) <hi>of Iſrael were come out of</hi> Sion! <hi>When the Lord bringeth back the Captivity of his People,</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall</hi> (or ought to) <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>ſhall</hi> (or ought to) <hi>be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to this, which is the moſt genuine Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56434:5"/>of the Pſalm, I may without the leaſt Violence to the Senſe of the Royal Pſalmiſt, make theſe three Obſervations upon my Text, which will be ſuitable to the Solemnity of this day.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the People in a State of prevailing, or ſucceſsful Rebellion, are in a State of Slavery, and Captivity.</hi> This Obſervation I ground upon that remarkable Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>the Captivity of his People.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That a People cannot be brought out of ſuch a State of Slavery, and Captivity, without the ſpecial Providence and Aſſiſtance of God.</hi> As it is written, <hi>when the LORD bringeth back the Captivity of his People.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That it is the Duty of a People ſo brought back out of Captivity, to render Praiſe and Thanksgivings unto God.</hi> When the Lord bringeth back the Captivity of his People, <hi>Jacob</hi> ought to rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to be glad.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, that a People in a State of prevaling, and Succeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rebellion are in a State of Slavery, and Captivity: for a State of Slavery and Captivity, conſiſts in being obnoxious to the will and pleaſure of an Unlimited, Abſolute, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power, ſuch as was the Power of the Ancient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperors,</hi> of whom as our Learned Lawyer <hi>Forteſcue</hi> obſerves out of <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Inſtitutions, the Civil Law ſaith, <hi>quod Principi placuit Legis habet Naturam, that the Princes pleaſure was a Law;</hi> Or, ſuch as was the Power of all Kings in the Kingdoms of Ancient Times, founded after the Flood, when, as <hi>Juſtin</hi> in his Epitome tells us, <hi>arbitria Regum pro Legibus erant, that the will of the King was a Law unto the People;</hi> Or laſtly, ſuch as is now the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Turkiſh, Ruſſian, Perſian,</hi> and <hi>Morocco Emperors,</hi> who rule purely by Regal Authority, without any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56434:6"/>Political Regulation, having Abſolute, Uncontrollable Power over the Lives, Fortunes, and Liberties of their People, and of whom I may truly ſay, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.19</note> 
               <hi>for the Majeſtly that the High God hath given unto them, all their People, Nations, and Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges tremble before them, for whom they will they ſlay, and whom they will they keep alive, whom they will they ſet up, and whom they will they pull down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay Civil Slavery, or Capativity, conſiſts in being obnoxious to ſuch an Unlimited Arbitrary Dominion, as this; which rather deſerves the name of <hi>Military,</hi> than Civil Power; but the People, that are Subject to a Conquering Rebel, or Rebels, are ſubject to ſuch an Unlimited, Abſolute, and Arbitrary Power, which is under no Civil Regulation, but as the forecited <hi>Forte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue,</hi> wiſely ſaith of <hi>meer Regal Power,</hi> it can give Laws to the People, and lay all manner to Taxes, and Burdens upon them without their conſent, and let me add, take away their Lives by a <hi>High Court of Juſtice,</hi> or by any other Arbitrary way, without Tryal by Law, or Peers, nay without any Tryal at all.</p>
            <p>For their Power is an Uſurped Military Power, not under the wholſom regulation of Laws, but as Arbitrary as the Sword, and as Tyrannical as their Luſts will make it, and if they do not oppreſs the People, after they have maſtered the Lawful Government, it is generally becauſe their Policy over rules their Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Cruelty, and not that they are truly good. It is ſeldom that Rebels have any regard, or tenderneſs to the Peoples Blood, or Treaſure; or if, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith of men who make their Intereſt their Supream End, <hi>the goodneſs of their Nature, may chance to over-rule their Evil Principles,</hi> yet the People, that are ſubject unto them, are all the while in the Lions Den, the Beaſt may perhaps be good humoured, and Generous, but ſtill he may eat them, when he will.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56434:6"/>
            <p>Therefore every ſucceſsful Rebellion makes the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Rebel a <hi>grand Seignior,</hi> the Sword is his Title, and his ſtanding Armies the Laws by which he Governs; ſo that in the moſt abſolute Monarchy that ever was, <hi>Rebellion</hi> may alter the Governors, but not the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which will be ſtill as Arbitrary, as the will and pleaſure of the Conqueror can make it, and all the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that People under ſuch a Revolution, can poſſibly reap by a proſperous Rebellion, will only be that of the Aſs in the Fable, who complained, that tho' he had changed his Maſter, and Paniers, very often, yet ſtill the burden was the ſame. I ſay in the moſt Arbitrary Government, where the People are perfect Slaves, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> will not likely mend their condition, becauſe the Conquering Rebels will ſtill be their Lords and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and they muſt ſtill abide Slaves. They change their Maſter, but not their Service, their Lords, but not their Vaſſallage; all the difference is, that they have an Uſurper, or Senate of Uſurpers, to rule over them, inſtead of their <hi>Natural Soveraign,</hi> and have ſet up their <hi>Fellow Subjects</hi> in his Place.</p>
            <p>This generally ſpeaking, is ſo true, and ſo agreeable to the common report of Hiſtories, that would the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the moſt Abſolute Monarch conſider it, they would never follow the moſt plauſible Ring-leader in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Rebellion againſt their Natural Soveraign; but moſt of all, would the People of a limited and regular Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, who have their Properties, and Liberties ſecured by Law, conſider, That a Conquering is an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, and Unlimited Power, they would abhor the thoughts, and abſtain from all appearance of Rebellion, which in the end muſt either render their own Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, or the Victorious Uſurpers, which is ten times worſe, abſolute Lords over them, and themſelves, by conſequence, perfect Slaves. For if their rightful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56434:7"/>againſt whom they rebell, prevail, then they and their Eſtates muſt ly at his mercy, and they will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent on any condition to redeem their forfeited lives; but if their pretended Patriots, their Leaders into Rebellion prevail, then <hi>They</hi> become their Abſolute Soveraign, and may diſpoſe of their Lives and Fortunes, without asking their conſent.</p>
            <p>What can hinder a ſucceſsful Traitor, at the Head of his Conquering Legions, from doing what he pleaſes? And who, even among thoſe who firſt ſet him up, and lent him their Aſſiſtance, dares ſay unto him <hi>What doſt thou?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.5.</note> At firſt he was their humble Servant, <hi>he did obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance unto them, and put forth his hand unto them, and kiſſed them;</hi> at firſt he ſighed for their unhappineſs, and bemoaned their Grievances, and begs but their own aſſiſtance to ſet them free; but as ſoon as he prevails, then they muſt ſay unto him, as the Trees ſaid unto the Bramble, in the Parable of <hi>Jotham, Come thou and reign over us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 9.14, 15.</note> and when it is once come to that, then he will plainly ſay unto them, <hi>If in truth ye anoint me King over you, then come and put your truſt in my ſhadow, but if not, let fire come out of the Bramble, and devour the Cedars of Lebanon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after <hi>Abſalom</hi> had ſtoln away the hearts of the People, by his fair Carriage and Speeches, the next News was, <hi>Abſalom reigneth in Hebron;</hi> and in his ſhort Reign, or Uſurpation, he and his Captains did ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave and oppreſs the Subjects of <hi>David,</hi> after they had revolted from him, that he compared their condition, under the Power of their young Idol, to Captivity; ſaying, <hi>When the Lord bringeth back the Captivity of his People; Jacob ſhall rejoice, and Iſrael ſhall be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had aſſured them before, that he deſired nothing more,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.4.</note> than to be in a condition to remove their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances: <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I were made a Judge in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56434:7"/>Land, that every man that hath any ſuit, or cauſe, might come unto me, and I would do him juſtice.</hi> This and ſuch like was his Language at firſt, but when he had got a great Army at his Command, and had beat the King out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then he could lye with his Father's Concubines upon the top of the Houſe, in the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he, and his Adherents, could <hi>eat up the people, as they eat bread.</hi> The poor oppreſſed Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty ſaw their own ſlavery too late, and when God beſides their expectation had delivered them from it, they were ſo glad of it, that they were at ſtrife through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Tribes, who ſhould bring the King back. <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaid the men of Iſrael) <hi>the King ſaved us from the hand of our Enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>he delivered us out of the hand of the Philiſtines, and now he is fled out of the Land for Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom, and Abſalom whom we</hi> rebelliouſly <hi>anointed over us is dead in Battel, now therefore why ſpeak ye not a word of bringing back the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations of the great Bleſſings they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed under <hi>David</hi> would weigh nothing with them before, but after they felt the Calamities of War, and the ſmart of Arbitrary Government under a prevailing <hi>Traitor,</hi> after they had run into that under <hi>Abſalom,</hi> which they had but feared under <hi>David,</hi> then they ſaw their Errour, and the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were angry with the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> for not letting them join with them in bringing back the King.</p>
            <p>And what happened unto the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> under the prevailing Rebellion of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> hath happened, I believe, upon all the ſucceſsful Rebellions in the World. Did ever People rebell with ſucceſs, and mend their condition by it? Nay, did ever People ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in Rebellion, and not afterwards groan under the Arbitrary Dominion of the Victorious Rebels? Or, were Grievances and Oppreſſions ever ſewer under
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56434:8"/>Uſurpers, than under the lawful Head? It is, as I have ſhewn, inconſiſtent with the Nature of that Arbitrary and Military Power, with which Conqueſt doth inveſt every proſperous Rebel; and though it be eaſie to reply, that it is poſſible for one that riſes up againſt his lawful Soveraign to be free from ſelf-intereſt and ambition, and purely to deſign the Eaſe and Liberty of his Fellow-Subjects; yet in all the Inſtances and Examples of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Rebellion, very few, or none ſuch are to be found. You ſee what Impoſtors <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel</hi> were, and how they falſified all their Pretenſions to the credulous People, and would the time permit, and the Solemnity of the day allow of it, I could verifie the truth of my firſt Obſervation in many ſuch Popular Cheats.</p>
            <p>But I will wave all Foreign, and confine my ſelf to Domeſtick Examples, to prove that a ſtate of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Rebellion is a ſtate of Slavery and Captivity, as King <hi>David</hi> in my Text, and our late Bleſſed Soveraign, who was wont to bewail the ſad condition of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the late prevailing Rebellion, frequently obſerved. I need not tell you what fair Promiſes, and gilded Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences the Ring-leaders of it made unto the deceivable People. They firſt poſſeſſed their Heads with imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fears, and Grievances, and then promiſed to ſecure them againſt all the Dangers which they feared. At firſt they exhorted and invited the Common Citizens and People, and then Commanded them; firſt they begg'd and borrowed Supplies of them, and took their Money by way of Contribution and Loan; but afterwards, when they had got the Power into their own hands, they levied it as faſt by their own Authority, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it by way of Tax. I ſhall ſay nothing of the illegality of their Rebellion againſt their Prince, no Law being better known to the People than that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56434:8"/>it <hi>to be High Treaſon to Levy War againſt the King,</hi> but I deſign to ſet forth their oppreſſion of their Fellow-Subjects, and ſhew in a few Inſtances how they inverted all the Fundamental Laws of the Engliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and how their little Finger was much heavier, then their Lawful Princes Loins.</p>
            <p>It is a Fundamental Law of the Engliſh Government, and the firſt Article of <hi>Magna Charta, Quod Eccleſia Anglicans libera ſit, &amp; habeat omnia ſua Jura integra, &amp; libertates illaeſas,</hi> That the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be free; and have all her Rights kept intire, and her Liberties inviolable, and yet to make Way for their Wicked, and ungodly Ends, they voted the Biſhops out of the Houſe of Peers, where, as Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> afterwards told them, they had ſat in their Predeceſſors as long as the Lords Temporal had ſat in their Progenitors, and longer than the Repreſentatives of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> had ſat in the Houſe of Commons. The Lords at firſt refuſed to conſent to ſuch a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal alteration, perceiving very well what might be the conſequence theoreof, upon which the People were brought down in Multitudes to the Parliament Doors, to Cry againſt the Biſhops ſeveral days ſucceſſively, till the Terrors of thoſe Tumults did force them to Conſent.</p>
            <p>After this was done to the Biſhops, they did what they pleaſed to the Loyal Clergy, and the Univerſities, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, and turning them out of their Free-Holds, in a moſt Arbitrary, and Tyrannical manner, as may be ſeen in a little Book called the IIth Perſecution, and many other Narratives of the late Times, to which I refer you for the particulars, that you may ſee how little regard theſe Patriots of <hi>England,</hi> falſly ſo called, had to the firſt Article of the <hi>great Charter,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Rights, and Liberties of the Church.</p>
            <p>But 2ly, It is a fundamental Law of the Engliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56434:9"/>
               <hi>That no Free Man ſhall be taken, or impriſoned, without Cauſe ſhewn, or be detained without being brought unto his Anſwer in due form of Law.</hi> This is part of the 29th Article of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the whole Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter of the 28th of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and of the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> which theſe very ſame Patriots, to endear themſelves unto the People, would not let the King reſt till he had paſſed again, and again. Yet after they had got the Sword into their own Hands, they Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned whom they would, thouſands of Innocent Men, and good Subjects of all Ranks, without aſſigning any Reaſon but the general Reaſon of <hi>Malignancy,</hi> and without bringing them to anſwer for themſelves, as the Law requires.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. It is a fundamental Law of the Engliſh Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>That no Man ſhall be diſſeized of his Free-hold, or Liberties, but by the known Laws of the Land.</hi> This likewiſe is contained in the 29th Article of the <hi>great Charter,</hi> and the 28th of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. And it is that, which makes <hi>England</hi> a Paradiſe, and the Engliſh the moſt happy People in the World: Yet theſe very Men from the moment they got the Power into their hands againſt all form of Law diſſeized, ſequeſtred, decimated, and forced Multitudes of Free-born Gentlemen of <hi>England</hi> to compound for their own <hi>Hereditary Eſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4ly. It is a fundamental Law of the Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, That no man ſhall be Condemned, or put to Death, but by lawful Judgment of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land in an ordinary way of a Legal Tryal.</hi> But theſe great Patriots, and Patrons of the Peoples Liberties, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned one of the Kings greateſt Subjects, by an <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Ordinance,</hi> made by the remaining Parts of both Houſes united into one; which made him ſay upon the Scaffold, <hi>that he was not only the firſt Arch-biſhop, but the firſt Engliſh-man, that dyed by an</hi> Ordinance <hi>of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56434:9"/>if the two Houſes ſitting without the King, and in open Hoſtility againſt him, much leſs, if a part of the two Houſes ſo ſitting, ought to be called by that happy, and Honourable Name.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is a fundamental Law of the Engliſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>That if any other caſe than what is declared in</hi> 25 Edw. 3. c. 2. <hi>which is ſuppoſed to be High Treaſon, do happen before any of his Majeſties Judges, thoſe Judges ſhall tarry without giving Judgment, till the Cauſe be ſhewn, and declared before the King and his Parliament, whether it ought to be judged High Treaſon, or no:</hi> Yet theſe Tyrannical Men, the <hi>remnant</hi> of a Rebellious Houſe, vote, and declared things to be High Treaſon, which could not be ſo by the Engliſh Laws, and which had never been declared to be High Treaſon, neither by the Law (by which they themſelves were Traitors;) nor by the Judges, in any Caſe; nor by the King and his Parliament; and by theſe, and other Arbitrary doings, they made the Free-born Subjects of this Nation, as meer Slaves, as the Subjects of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> and their Lives, and Liberties, their Goods, and Fortunes, as abſolutely depending upon them, as theirs depend upon him. It would be endleſs to recite all their Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanical Ordinances: Their Ordinances for Sequeſtring of Delinquents, as they called Loyal Perſons, Eſtates; for Taxing ſuch, as had not contributed to the War, or not contributed according to their Eſtates and Abilities; for ſequeſtring the Temporalities of many Biſhops, and then for ſelling all the Biſhops, and Church-Lands; for aſſeſſing all the Members of either Houſe, that abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from, or were in Arms againſt the Parliament, as they arrogantly miſcalled themſelves; for voiding the places of <hi>Clerks of Record,</hi> that did any thing in their Offices in Favour of the Crown; for regulating, as they called ruining, the two Univerſities; for removing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56434:10"/>of Scandalous, as they called Loyal, Miniſters; for taking away the fifth part of Delinquents Eſtates; for diſabling of them to bear any Office, or Place of truſt, or to have any Voice in Elections; for ſetting free all Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices from their Maſters, that had ſerved the Parliament; for Aboliſhing the Houſe of Peers; for ſelling the Kings Lands; not to mention all their new Devices, by which they ſqueezed out of the People of this Land, above twenty Millions in ſeven years Time: A Greater ſum than all the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> had levied from the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> until that time, or herhaps until this day.</p>
            <p>Their oppreſſions in theſe and ſuch like Inſtances were very viſible, not withſtanding all their Religious diſguiſes, and all their pretended Zeal for the Glory of God, inſomuch that great Complaints began to be made of them, by thoſe, who had ſet them up, and their Tyranny increaſing, at length came out a bold Remonſtrance againſt them in 1647, in which they are accoſted thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>Seeing it is high time for the <hi>Free Commons</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to look after the enjoyment of that good Land, Peace, Freedom, and Juſtice, which you <hi>promiſed us</hi> at the beginning, give us leave to expoſtulate a little: How comes it to paſs, that we reap not the Harveſt of this promiſed Seed-time, and that ſuch fair Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms yield ſuch ſlender Fruit? Whence comes this mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, and groaning, and theſe Exclamations againſt <hi>Oppreſſion, Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice</hi> in our ſtreets? How comes it to paſs, that we ſee <hi>Courts of Injuſtice</hi> (Juſtice we cannot call them) even at the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament-Door, nay, within the Parliament-Houſe? How comes it to paſs that ſo many <hi>Irregular</hi> and <hi>Illegal Votes,</hi> Orders, Declarations, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances paſs for current one day, and counterfeit the next? Whence proceeds this Spirit of <hi>Ambition, Contention, Oppreſſion, and Sedition,</hi> which Reigns ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56434:10"/>powerfully among you? Did you ſo vehemently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt Prerogative <hi>to deſtroy us by Priviledge?</hi> Did you Exclaim againſt Injuſtice in others, that your ſelves might be <hi>ſingularly, and ſuperlatively unjuſt? <hi>Must your Will be our Supream-Law?</hi>
                  </hi> Was the taking <hi>a little</hi> of our Eſtates illegal in others, but Juſtice in you to take <hi>all?</hi> Is this the end of our Labour, the return of our Expectation, and the prize, for which we have ſweat ſo much Blood? We looked for Juſtice, but behold <hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> we looked for Liberty, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Slavery,</hi> and our end is worſe than the beginning. We beſeech you to look to the Rock, from whence you are hewn; were you not <hi>Fellow-Commoners</hi> with us, and are you not accountable to us, by whom you are impowered, and intruſted? Have you not declared, that the Law ought to be the Rule of the Kings actions, and muſt it not be Rule of yours? Have you formerly declared, That they, who give Law to others, ought not to be without, or above Law themſelves? And therefore we the <hi>Free Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> expect reparation and relief againſt all your <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Exorbitant</hi> Practices. Have you not declared, That no Free Commoner ought, or might be diſinfranchiſed of his Liberty, without Indictment, and that the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Impriſoning of Men, without due Proceſs of Law, was a breach upon the Law, and deſtructive to the Subjects Liberty? How comes it then to paſs, that ſince the time of your declaring of it to <hi>be ſo unjuſt in others, you have ſo frequently uſed it your ſelves? What Priſon is there free;</hi> nay, what County, or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, but hath ſome Sufferers, being Impriſoned by the <hi>Arbitrary Subject-destroying Power</hi> of you, and your Committees? Have you not complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Publick Stock was converted to Private Uſes, and do not you do the ſame? And have you not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56434:11"/>often declared againſt the King, for keeping and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting Delinquents from Tryal, and do not you your ſelves protect, and defend many Falſe and <hi>Traiterous Members,</hi> under pretence of Priviledge.</q>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other Complaints in this Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance againſt our Reformers, which for Brevity-ſake, I omit. And after they were thus openly rebuked for their Oppreſſions, and Corruptions, their Credit began ſenſibly to decay, till at laſt they were diſſolved, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reformed into a new Council of State, which cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelves the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> which, after a ſhort blaze, reſigned all their Power to the <hi>Victorious Rebel,</hi> from whom they had it, under the ſtyle of <hi>Protector;</hi> and how the Nobility, Gentry, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and the whole Nation were enſlaved by him, his own Acts are yet extant to declare. He and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil made new Laws for Treaſon, and for levying and raiſing of Money. He confined a great part of the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Nobility, and Gentry, and ſuch as he ſuſpected of Loyalty, to their Houſes; he forbad them to wear Swords, and all others to meet at any Huntings, Horſe Races, and the like Diverſions. He made his Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations Laws, he tolerated all Religions, but Popery, and Prelacy, which he craftily joined together, to make the People believe they were both alike.</p>
            <p>He was ſucceeded by his Son, who was depoſed by the Officers of the Rebel-Army, they call back the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Old Long-Parliament to the Houſe; the Parliament preſently erects a Council of State, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they, and the Army claſh; the Army prevails, ſettles a Committee of Safety; this ſhortly expires, and is ſucceeded by the Remnant of the Long-Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. They preſently fall to Impriſon ſeveral of the moſt Eminent Citizens of <hi>London;</hi> and commanded the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> of happy memory, to take away their Poſts and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56434:11"/>Chains, and to deſtroy their Gates, and Portcullis's. As ſoon as he had done this, he bravely turned them out of Doors, and re-admits the <hi>Secluded Members,</hi> who ſeeing how the Kingdom was enſlaved, and bent upon the King's return, preſently iſſued out Writs for a free Parliament; which brought back his Majeſty upon this Auſpicious Day.</p>
            <p>From this Enumeration of the Uſurping Powers, you may perceive to what a degree this poor Nation was enſlaved, under ſo many Tyrannical Succeſſions. It is impoſſible to tell how many Souls, Lives, and Noble Families were deſtroyed by them, and how many Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſpent; but from this ſhort review, which I have now given you, you may perceive, that firſt I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to prove, <hi>That a People in a ſtate of Proſperous and Succeſsful Rebellion, are in a ſtate of Slavery and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity;</hi> but eſpecially a free People, who of Subjects to a limited Soveraign, under the Regulation of wholeſom Laws, become Slaves to the Arbitrary Power of their own <hi>Fellow Subjects,</hi> who Govern by the Sword.</p>
            <p>And ſo I paſs to my Second Propoſition to prove, That a People cannot be delivered out of ſuch a ſtate of Slavery, and Confuſion, without the ſpecial Providence and Aſſiſtance of God, as it is written, <hi>When the <hi>Lord</hi> bringeth back the Captivity in his People.</hi> This <hi>David,</hi> who was ſo great a King, and ſo great a Polititian, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth alſo to <hi>Zadock</hi> the High-Prieſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.25. <hi>The King ſaid unto</hi> Zadok <hi>the Prieſt, carry back the Ark of God into the City, if I ſhall find favour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bring me back again, and ſhew me both it, and his habitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Religious way of ſpeaking in <hi>David,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from <hi>Fear,</hi> or <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which is the Daughter of Fear, [for as <hi>Huſhai</hi> told <hi>Abſalom,</hi> he was a Valliant and Mighty Man] but from the rational
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56434:12"/>and experimental knowledge he had of the Being and Providence of God. He knew God, as a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and he knew him as a Prophet: Reaſon and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation had both taught him, how God cannot but be concerned in the moſt minute Contigencies, that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to ſingle Perſons, much more in the Revolutions of States and Kingdoms, according to what he elſewhere ſaith. <hi>The Lord is King for ever, and ever, he is a great King over all the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 47.2.</note> None but the <hi>Epicure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that over acknowledged the <hi>Being,</hi> denied the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> of God, and their Opinion is more unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than pure Atheiſm it ſelf; and all that ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Providence of God, did believe that he imployed it in a moſt ſpecial manner, over Human Societies, and that the greater any Human Societies were, they were the more ſpecial Objects of his Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Care.</p>
            <p>Indeed all Wiſe Men, both among <hi>Jews,</hi> Chriſtians, and Heathens, have thought it very difficult, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily preſurnptuous, to determine preciſely what things happen by Gods ſpecial Providence, and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and what do not; becauſe his ſecret Influences upon the Underſtandings, and Wills of Men, cannot be diſtinguiſhed from their own Judgment, and free Choice; but yet the Power, and Wiſdom, and Juſtice, and Goodneſs of God are ſo very diſcernable in ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, that we may without Preſumption impute them to him, as Judicious Criticks do Beoks to ſuch, and ſuch Authors, and from ſomething that is Divine in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of them, pronounce at firſt ſight, as a Limner did upon what was done in his abſence, on a Picture which he was drawing, that the hand of <hi>Apelles</hi> had been there. If you ask me what that is, which makes a Man diſcern the ſpecial hand of God in any Event, I might anſwer, without any prejudice to the Cauſe of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56434:12"/>Religion, that I cannot tell, becauſe the Characters of things, though clearly underſtood, are many times hard to be expreſſed: As in the appearance of a good, or bad Angel, that is inexplicable, which makes me diſcern, at firſt ſight, that what I ſee is not an ordinary Man.</p>
            <p>But leſt this ſhould look like ſhiſting, (as all lawful advantages will be called in the cauſe of God) I ſhall give you the Marks and Characters, which the Senſe of Mankind, and the Common Divinity of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hath ſet down, as Rules whereby to know, when any Humane Event is the Lords ſpecial doing, and in ſo doing, I ſhall apply the Wonderful Revolution from our Slavery and Captivity this Day, as a pat Example to every one of thoſe Rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Character then, whereby we may know, when any Event is the Lords ſpecial doing, or an Effect of his Special Providence, is, <hi>When it is brought about by Inviſible Means, or if by Viſible, yet by unlikely Means, which are Inadequate, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſuitable, or Repugnant to the Effect.</hi> For this Reaſon the <hi>Romans</hi> imputed that ſtrange Revolution of their good Fortune after the Battel at <hi>Cannae,</hi> to a ſpecial Over-ruling Providence, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowleged that <hi>Hannibal</hi> was Defeated by the Gods. <hi>Moventi a tertio lapide Hannibali Deos iterum, Deos, (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam) necfateri pudebit, reſtitiſſe,</hi> faith the Hiſtorian, which in alluſion to the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> may be rendered thus: <hi>If it had not been for the Gods, now may</hi> Rome <hi>ſay, if it had not been for the Gods, when the</hi> Carthaginians <hi>under</hi> Hannibal <hi>roſe up againſt us, they had ſwallowed us up quick, ſo wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully were they diſpleaſed at us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus likewiſe the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo amazed at the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Manner of their Deliverance out of Captivity, in which they had Lived 60 Years, that they were like Men in a Dream, and could ſcarce Believe the Truth,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56434:13"/>for the Strangeneſs of the thing. The Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Goodneſs of God was ſo Viſible in that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely revolution, that they could not hold from cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out among the Heathen, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us, the Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad.</hi> They eſteemed their Return from Captivity as great a Miracle, as turning back the Streams of <hi>Nile,</hi> and the Courſe of the Rivers in the South, and though there was nothing ſo ſurprizing in it, as in our Deliverance this Day, yet God repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it to the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> by the Reſurrection of Dry Bones, to ſhew it was his ſpecial Work. <hi>Son of Man</hi> (faith he to him in the <hi>Viſionary</hi> Valley full of Dry Bones) <hi>Propheſie upon theſe Dry Bones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. XXXVII.</note> 
               <hi>and ſay unto them: O ye Dry Bones, hear the Voice of the Lord! Thus ſaith the Lord to theſe Bones, I will breathe upon you, and you ſhall live, and know, that I am the Lord. So I Propheſied</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as I was Commanded, and there was a great Noiſe, and behold a great ſhaking, and the Bones came together, Bone to his Bone. And I beheld, and lo the Sinews, and Fleſh came upon them, and the Skin covered them above, but there was no Breath in them. Then ſaith he unto me, Propheſie unto the Wind, and ſay unto the Wind, Come, and Breathe upon theſe Slain, and I Propheſied as he commanded me, and the Breath came into them, and they lived, and ſtood upon their Feet, an exceeding great Army. Whereupon he ſaid unto me, Son of Man theſe Bones are the whole houſe of Iſrael.</hi> And for the ſame Reaſon may we now ſay, that they were the Loyal Captivated part of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects, whom God, as it were Raiſed out of their Graves, like Men, that had been long dead.</p>
            <p>The Prophecies are full of ſuch ingenious Emblems, as theſe, and particularly in the 17th <hi>Chap.</hi> of the ſame
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56434:13"/>Prophecy, God repreſented to the Prophet the Ruin and Reſtauration of the King, and Royal Houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> under the Parable of the Cedar, and great Eagle, which is as fit a Symbol to repreſent what hath happened to our late, and preſent Soveraign, and the <hi>Princes of the Blood.</hi> The great Eagle was the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who came to <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and cropt off the Branches of the higheſt Cedar, upon which it withered and dyed. <hi>But I</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>will preſerve the young twigs of the higheſt Cedar, and I will take the higheſt branch of it, and plant it again in the mountain of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and it ſhall put forth boughs, and bear fruit, and become a goodly Cedar, and all the trees of the Foreſt ſhall know</hi> (ſo ſignal was his Providence in it) <hi>that I the Lord brought down the high tree, and dried up the green tree, and made the dry tree to flouriſh again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was not this the condition of our late and preſent Soveraign? Did not an Eagle, a <hi>Many-headed</hi> Eagle full of Feathers of divers Colours, crop the top Boughs of the Royal Prerogative, and make the Cedar wither away, and dye? Nay, did they not do unto him, what was done to the Tree, in the viſion of <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, hew him down, cut off his branches,<note place="margin">Dan. 4 14.</note> ſhake his leaves, and ſcatter his fruit?</hi> But did not God preſerve his young Twigs, and did he not plant his higheſt Branch again in the Brittiſh Mountains, and is he not become a mighty Tree? Yes, there are ſo many things, if not plainly miraculous, yet ſo very admirable in the preſervation, and replanting of or Gracious Soveraign, that in Juſtice we ought to aſcribe it to the ſpecial over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Providence of God.</p>
            <p>For if we conſider the Builders, who refuſed the Stone; which is now become the head of the Corner, our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth-builders, I mean, who built with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Morter, Confuſion came upon them, as upon the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56434:14"/>Builders of <hi>Babel,</hi> none knows how, unleſs it was ſent from above. Conſternation ſuddenly fell upon ſome, Repentance or Horror ſeized upon others, and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Diſcontents confounded the reſt; the People in the mean while, as it were by Inſpiration, crying out in all places, <hi>Hoſannah to the King.</hi> Then were ſtrange things to be ſeen, Republicans with Royaliſts, Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with Church-robbers, Rebels and Traytors with Loyal Subjects, Papiſts with Proteſtants, Epiſcopiſts with Anti-epiſcoparians, all agreed to bring in the King, or let him be brought in. That Ethiopians ſhould thus change their Colour, and Leopards their Spots, that the Lyon ſhould aſſociate with the Lamb, and the Wolf with the Kid, that things on a ſudden ſhould change their Natures, or act againſt them, are Miracles in the Moral, as well, as the Natural World, and ought to be aſcribed to his Power, and ſpecial Providence, who only doth wonderful things.</p>
            <p>That Panick Fears ſhould alſo ſeize on thoſe <hi>Legions,</hi> of whom the World was afraid; and that they, who were <hi>Veterans</hi> in Blood, and Rebellion, ſhould bear the ſight of the Royal Standard, and pray for the King, as he paſſed their Ranks, muſt needs be imputed to his ſpecial Influence,<note place="margin">Zech. 12.10.</note> who was able <hi>to pour out the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication upon them, that they might look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, whom they had pierced</hi> with Repentance, and Remorſe. That ſo many different Elements ſhould jum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into ſuch an happy mixture, and Cauſes ſo contrary conſpire to one Effect, that all the Enemies of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhould be, as it were Planet-ſtruck, and all the Intereſts againſt it inviſibly ſubdued, that ſcarce one Party, or one Man among them ſhould appear to oppoſe this Revolution, nor one Dog among them move his Tongue, but that it ſhould be brought about without Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, without Murmur, or without a drop of Blood,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56434:14"/>was an admirable Scene of Affairs, worthy the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of infinite Wiſdom, and ought to be eſteemed, as his doing alone, who can work by repugnant Cauſes, bring Order out of Confuſion, and <hi>take from men their Hearts of Stone, and give them Hearts of Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Another Character of Gods ſpecial Providence and Aſſiſtance in any Event is, <hi>The ſtrange ſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, when it unexpectedly falls out in a time of deſpondency, to prevent the deſtruction of a deſtitute Perſon, and the utter ruine of a deſperate Righteous Cauſe.</hi> God could prevent the fall of good Men, and the ruine of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cauſes, but for juſt, and wiſe reaſons he ſometimes lets them lye in the rubbiſh, till they ſeem irreparable, and then unexpectedly raiſes them again, as our Saviour raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the Grave, when every one thought it was impoſſible to be done.</p>
            <p>This was the Condition of the Royal Family, and Cauſe. God could have prevented that ſtupendous Series of Calamities, which fell like Wave after Wave upon them, he could have prevented the Deſigns, and have ſooner blaſted the Succeſs of their Enemies, but he let them proſper to that degree, that the Spectators, as well as the Actors of this ſad Tragedy, were ready to think, that God had forgotten to be gracious to <hi>David,</hi> and had utterly forſaken his Righteous Cauſe. But then at the moment, when the Wicked Blaſphemed God, and ſaid, <hi>Tuſh! God careth not for him,</hi> in that Critical moment of Deſpair, when God ſeemed to <hi>ſtand afar off, and hid, as it were, his face from him,</hi> then he <hi>aroſe, and ſcattered his enemies, and broke the power of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> but like the power of the Tyrant <hi>Antiochus</hi> in <hi>Daniel</hi> which <hi>was broke without hands.</hi> When the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Will was a Law, when his Greatneſs made him defy his Enemies, and ſay in his Heart, <hi>I ſhall never be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56434:15"/>caſt down;</hi> then came a Diſeaſe, like an Angel ſent from God, to do the part of <hi>Brutus,</hi> and ſmote the Tyrant to the Ground. Even then, when there were no Human means left to rend the Kingdom from him, God rent him from the Kingdoms, and ſnatched his direful Soul from him, as from the Fool in the Goſpel, in the midſt of his ſtrength, and ſecurity, when he had taken the Houſes of God, and the Palaces of the King in poſſeſſion, and thought he had much Goods laid up for many years. When he ſaid in his Heart, <hi>I will aſcend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the Stars of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. XIV.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſit upon the mount of the Congregation in the ſides of the North,</hi> then I ſay, <hi>when he thought to aſcend above the clouds,</hi> (a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Symbol for Great Monarchy) <hi>and be like the moſt high</hi> in Soveraign Power, then fell he <hi>like</hi> Lucifer <hi>from Heaven, and was brought down to Hell,</hi> and then ſang we for joy, <hi>how art thou fallen from Heaven, O</hi> Lucifer! <hi>Son of the morning, how art thou cut down to the ground!</hi> Thou who didſt make the Earth to tremble, and ſhake the Kingdoms thereof. Laſtly, when he as brought to that prodigious Strength and Greatneſs, as to be Courted by the greateſt Monarchs, and thought to fix the Succeſſion in his tainted Blood; when he had been ſet by his Flatterers in a Throne, and the Crown and Scepter laid at the Idols Feet, <hi>then came the hand writing ſuddenly out againſt him;</hi> and the <hi>Stone,</hi> which he and the Builders before him had rejected, like <hi>the ſtone in the Viſion, cut out of the Mountain without hands, ſmote the Image</hi> (that Prophetical Symbol of many Governments) and broke in pieces the Iron, the Clay, the Braſs, the Silver, and the Gold, and they became like Chaff, and the wind carried them away, <hi>but the Stone, which ſmote the Image became a great mountain,</hi> even like <hi>mount</hi> Sion, <hi>which cannot be removed, and is the joy of the whole Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56434:15"/>
            <p>To conclude, even then when the Royal Intereſt was deſperate, and in Human probability muſt have utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly periſhed, had not the deliverance happened when it did, when not the People only, but the Princes of the Earth counted our Soveraign <hi>ſmitten, and afflicted of God,</hi> and ſhunned him, as the Heard do an hunted, or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſſed Stag, then ſudden confuſion came upon his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as ſorrow upon a Woman in Travel; then God ſaid of them, as of <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Anointed, <hi>He is my Shepherd,</hi> and ſet him upon the Throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and made his Enemies lick the Duſt. When he was ready to ſink under the Waves of Affliction, upon which he had walked, not without a Miracle, ſo many years, then didſt thou ſtretch forth thy Arm unto him, O righteous Jeſus, when he was <hi>become like a broken Veſſel, and ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed cleam forgotten, as a dead man out of ſight,</hi> then didſt thou, O Lord, <hi>overtun, overturn, overturn, till he came, whoſe right it was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Another Character of Gods ſpecial Providence, and Aſſiſtance in any Event, is. <hi>The mighty good, which thereby accrues to the publick ſtate of things, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon whoſe welfare the publick doth depend.</hi> To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe every petty Accident to a ſpecial Providence, would look like Lightneſs, and Superſtition, and it would be Profaneſs to father upon God the miſchieſs, which we bring upon our ſelves, by our own Sin, and Folly, but that <hi>great and beneficial Events</hi> ought to be aſcribed to his particular hand, is the common Creed of all Mankind. For it is demonſtrable from the Nature, and Attributes of God, that he doth govern Human Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and that being admitted, it muſt needs follow in the Second place, that he takes ſpecial care in ordering thoſe Events, which are of publick moment and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to Mankind, and peculiarly thoſe, which concern a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56434:16"/>People, that are of his Houſhold, which is the Church of God. There was never any thing, which ſeemed more contingent, than the ſelling of <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> yet God did order it by a ſpecial Providence, that he might be an Inſtrument in the time of Dearth, of ſaving his Fathers Houſe. <hi>It was not you,</hi> (ſaith he to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) <hi>but God, who ſent me hither to preſerve you a Poſterity on the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 45.5, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>God ſent me before you, to ſave your lives by this great deliverance, and hath made me a father to</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and Lord of his hourſe, and Ruler throughout all the land of</hi> Egypt, which was then more than ever the Granary of the World. So likewiſe in the ſtory of <hi>Eſther,</hi> that ſhe ſhould be choſen into the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of <hi>Aſhuerus</hi> among a crowd of other Virgins, ſeems a matter of Fortune, or common Providence, and yet it was contrived by God, for the deliverance of his People, and the Providential Scene, which depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, was perhaps, as miraculous, as ever was acted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage of Human Affairs.</p>
            <p>But of all the remarkable Events in Sacred, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fance Hiſtory, none hath been a greater Bleſſing to any Prince, or People, than the Revolution of this day hath been to us, and our King. As for us, we were delivered by it from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> at home, from dome-ſtick Captivity, from Servitude of all Servitudes the moſt intolerable, under the Tyrannical Empire of our own <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malukes,</hi> and from that <hi>Evil under the Sun,</hi> when Beggars and Servants were Lords and Princes, and Princes and Lords, Beggars and Slaves. We were delivered by it from Military and Arbitrary Power indeed, from the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Inſolence of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping Sultans</hi> in ſeveral Forms and Succeſſions of Government, who broke the bonds of Law in ſunder, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did the green Withs, like Threds of Tow, and made their Will and Pleaſure our Law. In a word, we were reſtored by it to our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56434:16"/>King, and Government to the Father of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and in him to our Lives, our Religion, our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>his Majeſty,</hi> he was reſtored by it to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of Three Kingdoms, where <hi>his Dominion is from one Sea to the other, and from the Flood unto the Worlds end:</hi> Of Three Kingdoms, where his Subjects are his Children, and where even <hi>his Merchants,</hi> as the Prophet Speaks, <hi>are Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 23.8.</note> 
               <hi>and <hi>his Traffiquers</hi> the Honourable of the Earth:</hi> Laſtly, of Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, where he ſits on his Throne, like God, holding the Ballance of the World, and repreſents him above all other Monarchs in this, that he is the Moderator of Peace and War among Princes, and can Set up one, and Pull another down.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Temporal Bleſſings, which he, and we enjoy by it, and the Spiritual are no leſs conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than theſe. For after our return from Captivity, the Temple was ſoon Rebuilt, the Altar ſpeedily ſet up, and the Lawful Prieſthood reſtored again. Wherefore, ſince the revolution of this Day was ſuch an unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bleſſing to the Three Nations, and ſo highly benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial both to Church and State, common Reaſon, and Religion will Award the Contrivance of it to Gods Wiſdom, and the Execution of it in all its parts to his Almighty Arm.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Another mark of Gods Special Providence, and aſſiſtance in any Event, is, <hi>When it falls out very ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly for the relief, and Vindication of oppreſſed Innocence, and brings along with it the juſt Execution of publick Vengeance, upon the</hi> Nimrods <hi>of Humane Societies, the Sons of violence, who live by Oppreſſion and Prey.</hi> God is naturally the Protector of Innocent Men, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Cauſes, and tho' in Wiſdom he cannot acquit, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56434:17"/>condemn, reward, and puniſh here, as he means to do hereafter, when the great <hi>Tragecomedy</hi> is done; yet, leſt in the mean time the Spectators ſhould have Siniſter Thoughts of his Providence, he is forced to come as it were, from behind the Curtain, and kill a Bloody Tyrant, like <hi>Herod,</hi> with Blaſphemy perhaps in his Mouth, and ſitting in his Royal appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel upon his Throne. Though it would be inconſiſtent with his Wiſdom in the Preſent State of things, to extirpate the Bears and Wolves of Humane Societies, yet, like <hi>David,</hi> when he tended his Fathers Flock, he often ſmites the Lyon, and the Bear, and reſcues the Lamb out of their Paws; and tho' the Nature of this inferiour Oeconomy obligeth him to ſcourge Sinners by the Hands of Wicked Men, yet <hi>the Rod of the Wicked ſhall not always reſt on the Lot of the Righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 125.3.</note> 
               <hi>leſt they put forth their Hands unto Iniquity.</hi> He knows our Frame, and remembers that we are but Duſt, and therefore in his Puniſhments, he hath regard to the Strength of the Patient, as well, as to the merits of his Crimes. Hence it proceeds, that in the midſt of Judgment, he remembers Mercy, and that afflicted Perſons, and Nations, are ſo often relieved; as we were, in a Time of Deſpondency, even then, when we feared, that his Mercy was clean gone, and that he would be intreated no more. We had tempted, and provoked the moſt High to be wroth with his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo that he gave us over unto the Sword, and our <hi>Glory</hi> into Rebellious Hands. He would not go forth with his Armies againſt them, but let them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute his Righteous Soul, and take it, and lay his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Duſt; Yet tho' all this came upon us, he did not forget us, but after ſo many, and ſuch long Miſeries both in Church, and State, he awoke, as one out of Sleep, and like a Mighty Man refreſhed with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56434:17"/>Wine, he ſmote our Enemies in the hinder parts, and put them to a perpetual ſhame: Tho' the Rod, with which he ſmote us, ſeemed for ſome Years to Bloſſom in his Hand, yet, when his Anger was over, he broke it, and threw the Pieces into the Fire.</p>
            <p>The faithful Royaliſts, and their Prince were deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, afflicted, and tormented, they wandred ſome of them in Deſarts, and Mountains, and ſome in Dens, and Caves of the Earth. They had Tryal of moſt cruel Mockings, moreover of Bonds, and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being faſt bound in Miſery, and Iron, which entered into their Soul. As it is written, for his Sake were they killed all the day long, and counted as Sheep appointed to be Slain. Yet, for all this, he aroſe in his Good Time and Delivered them; the ſorrowful ſighing of the Priſoners, and Exiles came before him, as the Cry of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and he delivered them, by the Death of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> out of their Diſtreſs. The Voice of their Blood, like that of Righteous <hi>Abels,</hi> cryed unto him from the Ground, nay the Soul of our Martyred Soveraign, not to mention the High Prieſts, cryed, like the Souls of the Martyrs under the Altar, cryed with a loud, and bitter Voice, <hi>How long, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Holy, and True, doſt thou not Judge, and Avenge our Blood?</hi> And when he had reſted a little while, till the number of his Faithful Subjects, the true <hi>Melchites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which ſhould be ſlain, were fulfilled, <hi>Then didſt thou, O Lord, to whom Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance belongeth, ſhew thy ſelf, then didſt thou lift up thy ſelf, O thou Judge of the Earth.</hi> The Lord made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be known by the Judgments, which were executed upon the Murderers of our <hi>Martyred Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</hi> whom, tho' they proſpered ſo many Years after, to the Grief, and Aſtoniſhment of Good Men, yet Vengeance wonderfully purſued and ſuffered not to live,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56434:18"/>but as they had ſhed the Blood of the Saints, ſo divine Vengeance in retaliation gave them Blood to drink. Nay the Juſlice of God ſignalized her ſelf on the Chief Contriver of the Royal Tragedy, whom his Patience had ſuffered to go to the Grave in Peace. For he, and his Chief Fellow-Actor were <hi>caſt out of their Graves, like an abominable Branch, and as Carcaſſes of Beaſts they were drawn, and carried out beyond the Gates of</hi> our Jeruſalem, <hi>and buried</hi> again <hi>with the Burial of an Aſs.</hi> The World indeed expected, that publick Juſtice, like the Angel in the Revelations, ſhould have thruſt in her Sickle, and gathered the Cluſters, that were ripe for the Wine-preſs of her Wrath, and that ſhe ſhould have trodden them without the City, till Blood ſhould have come out of the Wine-preſs even unto the Horſes Bridles, but being moderated by the Mercy of our reſtored Soveraign, upon whoſe Throne ſhe attends, ſhe contented her-ſelf with a few of the ripeſt Cluſters. Tho ſhe expected <hi>to have waſhed her Feet in the Blood of the ungodly,</hi> yet ſhe ſatisfied her ſelf with Drops inſtead of Buckets, and like the Deſtroying Angel put up her Sword, when ſhe might have made it Drunk with their Blood.</p>
            <p>Indeed there was enough of it ſhed, for the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Divine Juſtice, and the full ſatisfaction of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Ghoſts, yet however it is obſervable, and perhaps too not without a Divine Providence, that ſome of thoſe <hi>Arch-Traytors,</hi> who owed their forfeited Lives to the King's Mercy, ſhould remain in the Land, like the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to be pricks in our Eyes, and Thorns in our Gracious Monarchs ſides.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Another Indication of Gods ſpecial Providence, and Aſſiſtance in any event, is, <hi>The Harmony of its parts, when various accident, happily conſpire,</hi> as in this Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>to produce the ſame effect.</hi> That one, or two
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56434:18"/>things ſhould luckily hit in the Production of ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Event, may perhaps be reaſonably aſcribed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Providence, or Chance, but that ſo many different Intereſts ſhould combine, and ſo many accidents at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, and divers places, ſhould all concurr, as it were by deſign, to work the deliverance of this day, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without manifeſt Violence to common Reaſon, but be aſcribed to his particular Contrivance, who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to range ſo many Cauſes in Order, and judge of the Seaſons, and Junctures of Affairs. As Nature is nothing but Divine Art; ſo ſuch admirable revolutions can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Divine Artifice, and Contrivance; unleſs it can be imagined, that a thing wherein there is ſo much of Plot, and which was ſo curiouſly contrived, that no Human Wiſdom could wiſh it, or contrive it better, may reaſonably be imputed to Chance. An ingenious <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as a more ingenious Author of our own tells us, hath written a Book, to prove te being of God, from the admirable contrivance of that ſhadow of his inviſible Glory, the Sun, becauſe, as he well obſerves, neither many Suns, nor one any otherwiſe contrived, than this is, could have ſerved the ſame noble purpoſes ſo well. For had there been two, or any other number of Suns, or had this ſtood ſtill, or been bigger, or leſſer, or ſet at other diſtance, or had its motion been any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way ordered, than it is, great and manifold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences in Nature would have followed thereupon: Wherfore ſince it is already contrived ſo well, both as to its bigneſs, diſtance, and motion, that the wit of Men and Angels could not contrive it better, Reaſon muſt, and ought to preſume, that it was contrived by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom God. In like manner, had I time to ſet before you the ſeveral parts, and circumſtances of this wonderful Revolution, I am confident, I could make it appear, that it had been attended with many notable inconveniencies, had it happened at any other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56434:19"/>time, or in any other manner, or by any other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, than it did. Wherefore is it not moſt reaſonable to conclude, that it was the Conſult of a ſpecial Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſince it was contrived in a manner ſo apparently worthy of the Divine Wiſdorn, and ſince the united Reaſon of Men and Angels, could not have contrived it in a better way, than it really fell out. Certainly the ſeaſonable contrivance of ſo many wonderful Scenes into every Act, and of ſo many currious Acts into one harmonious Play, muſt needs have been the ſtudy and invention of a very skilful Author, even of the All-wiſe, and Almighty Dramatiſt; who hath the World for his Theatre, and ſeldom leſs than a Kingdom for his Stage.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Another ſign of Gods ſpecial Providence, and Aſſiſtance, is, when a remarkable Event happens to any, eſpecially to Publick, and Illuſtrious Perſons, upon the ſame day, in which another Accident, as remarkable, as that,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.41.</note> happened to them before. So the ſame day that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went into <hi>Egypt; At the end of</hi> 430 <hi>years it came to paſs on the ſelf ſame day, that all the hoſts of the Lord went out from thence.</hi> So the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar was providentially ſet up by <hi>Judas Macchabeus,</hi> on the ſelf ſame day it had been profaned by the Tyrant <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> and ſo, as our Church hath well obſerved, it was not without a ſpecial Providence, that on the ſelf ſame day, in which our Soveraign was born, he ſhould, as it were be born again, in being reſtored to his Triple Crown.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Another Rule whereby to know when any Event is brought about by Gods ſpecial Providence and Aſſiſtance, is, the Correſpondency of it to the Prayers of Good Men, eſpecially of the King, and the Church. The Prayers of the Faithful, of Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56434:19"/>Kings eſpecially, as of <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> and <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> not to mention others, both <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and Chriſtian Kings and Em peroursavail very much. Nay, we read of a <hi>Turkiſh King,</hi> who by a ſhort Prayer to Chriſt in the midſt of a Battel, turned the fortune of it, when it was deſperate, againſt the perfidious Chriſtians, who had horribly perjured their Saviour's Name. But when a King, eſpecially a King ſo Holy, and Juſt as our late moſt bleſſed Soveraign, ſhall Kneel before him, who ſits upon the Throne, and caſt his Crown at his Feet: When a King ſo dear unto God, as he was, ſhall beg a Bleſſing of him, almoſt with his laſt Breath, as he did the deliverance of this Day, there is great Reaſon to look upon the performance of it, as a ſpecial Anſwer to ſuch prevailing Prayers. <hi>The King, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 21, 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in thy Salvation, for thou haſt granted him his Hearts deſire, and haſt not denved him the requeſt of his Lips.</hi> But when not only <hi>the Beaſts,</hi> (thoſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Emblems of Kings) but <hi>the four, and twenty El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> by which are meant Chriſtian Biſhops, I ſay, when not only Chriſtian Kings, but Biſhops, the chief Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and the whole Church over which they preſide, ſhall caſt themſelves down before the Lamb, to acknowledg their ſins, and beg a deliverance of God, then, if ever, muſt the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffer Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and God appear to be a God, that heareth Prayers.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeeing it is the property of the infinitely Merciful God to <hi>hear Prayers,</hi> eſpecially the united Prayers of the King, and the Church, we have juſt preſumption to aſcribe this deliverance, to his Special Favour in hearing thheir Conſpiring Sighs, and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For if two, as our Saviour ſaid, much more if a whole Church, ſhall agree on Earth, touching any thing they ſhall ask, it ſhall be done for them of our Father, which is in Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56434:20"/>
            <p>Such are the Characters of Gods ſpecial Providence, and Aſſiſtance, whereof any one, appearing in any event, is ſufficient to juſtify the imputation of it to the <hi>ſpecial hand</hi> of God. But that they ſhould all be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in one Event, that ſuch a mighty Revolution ſhould be effected by very improbable means, and fall out ſo ſeaſonably, to prevent the Deſtruction of a deſtitute exiled Prince, and the utter ruine of a deſperate Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Cauſe, and a pure Apoſtolical Church; that ſo much unſpeakable good doth accrue by it to the Publick, and that Oppreſſed right and innocency were thereby relieved, and publick Juſtice done upon the Sons of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation and Blood, that ſo many various accidents ſhould ſo happily conſpire to bring it about, and that it ſhould happen upon the ſame day, which was remarkable before for the appearance of the Star, and our Soveraigns Birth. Laſtly, that it ſhould fall out in correſpondence to the Prayers of good men, eſpecially of the King, and of all, that had kept their Garments un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted in this ſuffering Apoſtolical Church: Such a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Complication of all theſe marks in one Event, muſt needs force all, but Atheiſts, or Epicureans, who are more abſurd than Atheiſts, to confeſs with <hi>David,</hi> that it was the Lord, <hi>who brought back our Captivity,</hi> and cry out with the Church in the 118th Pſalm, <hi>This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi> Which brings me in the <hi>third place</hi> to conſider the duty, which a People ſo wonderfully brought back from Captivity ought to perform, which, I told you, was <hi>to render praiſes, and thanksgivings to God,</hi> as it is written in my Text, <hi>When the Lord bringeth back the Captivity of his People,</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall,</hi> or ought, to <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall,</hi> that is, ought to <hi>be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the import of theſe Phraſes of rejoycing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glad. They ſignifie Religious joy, and gladneſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing it ſelf, and exulting in praiſes, and thankſgivings
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56434:20"/>unto God. So in the 118 <hi>Pſalm</hi> which the Royal Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt made after he was Anointed King of <hi>Iſrael. The voice of rejoycing, and Salvation is in the Tabernacles of the Righteous, the Right hand of the Lord bringeth mighty things to paſs, the Right hand of the Lord is exalted, the Right hand of the Lord bringeth mighty things to paſs. The Stone which the Builders refuſed is become the Head-ſtone of the Corner, this is the Lords doing and it is marvellous in our Eyes, this is the day, which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce, and be glad therein, bind the Sacrifice with Cords even unto the Horns of the Altar, thou art my God, and I will Praiſe thee, thou art my God, I will Exalt thee, O give thanks unto the Lord, for be is good, for his Mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almoſt all the Pſalmes of Praiſe and Thanks-giving are full of expreſſions of Joy and Gladneſs, becauſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious joy is the Fountain, from whence all Praiſes and Thanksgivings do proceed, and the proper paſſions, and diſpoſitions of mind which make them acceptable unto God. Therefore ſaith the Pſalmiſt in another Pſalm, <hi>O le joyful in the Lord, O ye Lands! Serve the Lord with Gladneſs, and come before his preſence with a Song.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This we have done, and this ſtill is our Duty to do on this auſpicious Day. We have offered up the Calves of our Lips, the Sacrifices of Praiſes and Thanksgivings unto God with our Mouths, and I hope our Hearts are Uniſons with our Tongues. <hi>We have ſung unto the Lord,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, and heartily rejoiced in the ſtrength of our Salvation, we have <hi>ſung Pſalms and Anthems</hi> unto him, becauſe he hath done marvellous things, and, I hope in this ſolemnity our very <hi>Souls have magnified the Lord, and our Spirits have rejoyced in God our Saviour,</hi> and even hto te laſt moment of it, let every Loyal Perſon ſay,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56434:21"/>
               <hi>bleſs the Lord O my Soul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 103.1.</note> 
               <hi>and all that is within me, bleſs his Holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly it is our duty on this happy day to extol God, and exult in the Salvation, which he hath wrought for us, and to acknowledge <hi>that this is the day which the Lord hath made,</hi> the day of our going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the day of our return from Captivity, the day of the Dedication of our Temple and Altar, nay the day of the <hi>Brittiſh Purim</hi> in which we ought to rejoyce, as being the day, <hi>wherein we reſted from our Enemies, and the month which was turned to us from Sorrow to Joy, and from mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into a good day, that we ſhould make it a day of Feaſting, and Joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>and of ſending Portions, and guifts to the Poor,</hi> For it is to the Mercy of this day, that we owe our Lives, our Religions our Liberties, and Eſtates, that every one of us can ſit ſecurely under his own Vine, and call what he hath his own, and therefore certainly, we that ejoy ſo great a Deliverance by this day, and ſuch mighty Bleſſings conſequent upon it, as <hi>no other People</hi> in the World enjoy beſides our ſelves, if our hearts be not at diſcord with our Mouths in our preſent Devotions, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear to let the offerings of our Charity, accompany our Sacrifices of Praiſe, and do ſomething conſiderable to exhilarate the Spirits of our poor brethren, and make them partakers of our joy. This day the ſorrowful ſighing of the Poor, and of the Priſoners ought to come before us, and more eſpecially if we know any ſuch, who wereruined by the late Succeſsful Rebellion, them we ought to relieve. They, more eſpecially, ought to be the Objects of your Charity upon this Solemnity, and therefore in the firſt place let us do good, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to thoſe, or the Poor Relations of thoſe who were ſufferers for their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and bore the greateſt and bittereſt part of that Captivity, from which the Lord
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56434:21"/>brought back his People upon this day. I ſuppoſe there are ſuch to be found among you, the Monuments of your former Loyalty in the <hi>bloody Worceſter-fight,</hi> and I hope you will conſider them as Martyrs, and Confeſſors for our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, and open your hand liberally towards them, who yet bear in their Bodies, or in their Diſtreſſed Families the Marks of their Loyalty for the King, and of their Sufferings for the Church. We cannot offer up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God any Sacrifice more acceptable, than the ſupplies, which, in gratitude to him for our Deliverance, we ſhall give to them this day, and if our Charity be ſuch, as becomes our preſent Devotion, we need not fear, but that God will accept our Alms and Oblations, and that our Prayers and our Alms will go up for a Memorial before him, who hath done ſo great things for us, and by his Almighty Power, and Allwiſe Providence turned our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, as the Rivers in the South.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the duties proper to this day, but then we muſt further underſtand, that if our Joy be pure and genuine, and ſuch as really proceeds from a grateful, and Religious Senſe of Gods Goodneſs, it will ſhew it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Fruits of true Piety towards God, and of True, and conſcientious Allegiance to the King, (whom God ſo miraculouſly reſtored unto us) all the Days of our Life.</p>
            <p>He that pretends Religion towards God, and yet makes uſe of it, as a Cloak of Maliciouſneſs to Cover his Diſaffection, and Diſloyalty to the King, that Mans Religion, let him ſhew never ſo much Zeal for preſerving the Proteſtant Religion, is Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical, and vain, and utterly unacceptable in the ſight of him, who will have every Soul to be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Higher Powers: And on the other hand,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56434:22"/>he who pretends Loyalty to the King, and expreſſes it in ſuch a manner as muſt needs be offenſive to God, and ſober Men, that mans Loyalty ſubverts the Kings Throne, and provokes God to let the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Crown multiply, and proſper, to puniſh the Wickedneſs of ſuch profane Royaliſts, who in that <hi>Bacchanal</hi> manner, by which they Teſtify their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the King, diſgrace his Majeſty, and diſhonour God. He that truly Fears God will Honour the King, and not meddle with thoſe, that are given to Change, and he that truly Honours the King, in the Chriſtian notion of a King, as the Image and Lieutenant of God, will be ſure to Honour him, by whom Kings Reign, and expreſs his Zeal for him, and his Joy for his Reſtauration in ſuch Ways and Meaſures, as ſhall not pollute any Feſtival So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, or turn our indulgence into Riot or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. God forbid that <hi>Loyalty</hi> more than any other Chriſtian Virtue, ſhould be made a pretenſe for ſuch unworthy <hi>Greek</hi> Practiſes, and God forbid, that any of the Engliſh <hi>Melchites,</hi> or Loyal Subjects of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould find no other ways of declaring their Zeal, and Affection for their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, than ſuch as will render them the Scorn, and Reproach of theirs, and the Kings Enemies, and a Scandal to the Royal Cauſe. Let us in God's Name rejoyce in the Kings Salvation, but in ſuch a manner, as will conſiſt with the ſtrict Rules of Chriſtian Sobriety. Let the Fear of God temper our Mirth for the Deliverance of the King, let us wiſh him Health, and ſay with <hi>Daniel,</hi> O King live for Ever; but at the ſame time let us remember him, who hath Cloathed him with Majeſty, and in whoſe Rule, and Governance the Hearts of Kings and Princes are. God indeed hath given Wine to chear the Heart
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56434:22"/>of Man, but then we muſt in our Mirth remember what he hath told us, <hi>that Wine is a Mocker, and that ſtrong drink is rageing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 20 1.</note> 
               <hi>and whoſoever is deceived thereby is not Wiſe.</hi> God indeed hath given us leave to Eat, and Drink, to <hi>kill Beaſts, to mingle our Wines, and furniſh our Tables upon</hi> Feſtivall Occaſions, but then, as Chriſtians, it becomes us to remember at our Feaſts, <hi>that whether we eat, or drink,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we doe, we muſt do it to the Praiſe, and glory of God,</hi> who on this day brought back the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of his People, and therefore doth expect, that <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould Rejoice, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be Glad, for the wonderful deliverance, which by his Special. Providence and Aſſiſtance he hath brought about Now to God, our Mighty Deliverer and Saviour, who giveth Victory unto Kings; the God to whom alone our Gracious Soveraign is Subject, and next under whom he is Supream, within theſe Realms, unto the Allwiſe, and Almighty God, of whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution Kings and Kingdoms are; unto the Allwiſe Almighty God and Creator, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, Eternal Praiſe, Honour. Majeſty, and Glory by us, and by the whole Church Militant and Triumphant, now and Evermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <p>Page 17, <hi>line penult, for</hi> 60, <hi>read</hi> 70.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:56434:23"/>
            <head>Sermons written by the ſame Authour, and Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhops-head in St. <hi>Pauls-Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. A</hi> Diſcourſe to prove the ſtrongeſt Temptations are conquerable by Chriſtians. A Sermon Preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and Court of Aldermen, <hi>Jan. 14th 1676/7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Spirit of <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> Exorciſed, In a Sermon Preached before the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> On <hi>Act-Sunday, 1680.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Peculium Dei,</hi> A Sermon Preached before the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Aldermen and Citizens of <hi>London</hi> on <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary 6th, 1688/8 0/1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The true Notion of Perſecution, in a Sermon preached at the time of the late Contribution for the <hi>French Proteſtants.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> A Sermon Preached before the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Citizens of London, on <hi>Jan. 30th 1681/2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> The Moral <hi>Shechinah,</hi> or a Diſcourſe of Gods Glory, In a Sermon Preached at the <hi>York-ſhire</hi> Feaſt In <hi>Bow-Church, June 11 1682.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> A Sermon Preached at the Church of St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter-Tueſday,</hi> being the firſt of <hi>April 1684,</hi> before the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Henry Tulſe</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> and the Honourable Court of Aldermen, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with he Governours of the Hospitals upon the Subject of Almsgiving.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:56434:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
